President's Office Records, 1927-1981
University of Houston Libraries
President's Office Records
1927-1981
University of Houston. Office of the President
The University of Houston was founded in 1927 as the Houston Junior College, operated by the Houston Independent School District. In 1934, the school was renamed the University of Houston and became a four-year college. The President's Office Records include correspondence, memoranda, publications, clippings, invitations, and related material dating from 1927-1981 that were received or created by the President of the University of Houston.
63 boxes; 62 linear feet
1985-005
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Historical and Biographical Note
Historical Note
The University of Houston was founded in 1927 as the Houston Junior College, operated by the Houston Independent School District. In 1934, the school was renamed the University of Houston and became a four-year college. In 1940, the first graduate degrees were awarded in the field of education. In 1945, the University became a separate, private entity with its own Board of Regents, chaired by Hugh Roy Cullen. Throughout this period E. E. Oberholtzer was the president of the University.
In 1950, W. W. Kemmerer became acting president of the University. Kemmerer served as president from 1952 to 1953, when C. F. McElhinney became acting president. General A. D. Bruce, who served as president until 1956 when he became chancellor of the University, followed him in 1954. Clanton W. Williams became president in 1956. In 1961, Philip G. Hoffman became president of the University of Houston. He held this position until 1977, when he became president of the UH System.
Biographical Notes
Edison E. Oberholtzer
From 1924-1927 Oberholtzer served as Superintendent of the Houston Independent School District. With the formation of the Houston Junior College in 1927 he was named president. He remained president through the change from a two-year to a four-year institution in 1934 and continued until shortly before his death in 1950.
Walter W. Kemmerer
In 1929 Oberholtzer offered Kemmerer the position of Director of Curriculum and Research with Houston Independent School District. He remained in this position until June 1934, when he was appointed vice-president of the University of Houston. In October 1943, the position of "vice-president" was eliminated and Kemmerer's title was changed to Comptroller and Director of Curriculum. In spring 1944 Oberholtzer created the office and title "Assistant to the President" for Kemmerer. With Oberholtzer's retirement in 1950 Kemmerer became first acting president on June 1, 1950 and president on April 15, 1952. He was asked to resign on April 27, 1953.
Charles Flemming McElhinney
Charles Flemming McElhinney (commonly known as C. F. McElhinney or "Mr. Mac") moved to Houston in 1934, taking the position of Assistant Director of Curriculum and Research for the Houston Independent School District from 1934-1939. He became Director of Research from 1939-1945, and business manager for the University of Houston which, until 1945, was operated by the Houston Independent School District. During this time he also served as a staff assistant to E. E. Oberholtzer. From 1945 until his retirement in 1973, McElhinney served as the business manager of the university. He also served as interim president of the University from 1953-1954, a position he agreed to serve in to allow time for the Board of Regents to select a new President.
Andrew Davis Bruce
General Andrew Davis (A.D.) Bruce was the third president and the first chancellor of the University of Houston. Bruce became president of the university on September 1, 1954 and chancellor in December 1956. He retired from the university after the 1960-61 academic year. In 1957 Bruce organized a Board of Governors, composed of the regents of the university and prominent Houstonians. In November 1959 the governing board sought state support for the University, which had grown rapidly in the preceding years. Bruce was one of the first to advocate tax support for the University of Houston.
Clanton W. Williams
Clanton Ware Williams served as the fourth president of the University of Houston from 1956-1960. Williams joined the University of Houston as Vice-President for Academic Affairs in January 1955. He was named president of the University at the December 10, 1956 meeting of the Board of Regents. At this same meeting, A.D. Bruce was named chancellor and chief executive officer of the university. With this new reporting structure, the president was entrusted with the internal affairs while the chancellor was charged with both external relationships and overall responsibility. From August 11, 1960 to September 1, 1961, Williams retained the title of president, but was on a leave of absence.
Philip G. Hoffman
In 1957 Philip Guthrie Hoffman came to the University of Houston as Vice President and Dean of Faculties. He was appointed as the fifth president of the University of Houston in September 1961, and was officially inaugurated on April 27, 1962. Hoffman served as president until 1977, when he became president of the University of Houston System. He remained in this position until his retirement in 1979. Some of the advances made during Hoffman's tenure include reorganization and augmentation of administrative staff, including shifts within the ranks of the academic deans; conducting an institution-wide self-study; completing a new master plan for campus development; and taking first steps toward the formation of a University of Houston System.
Scope and Contents
In 1985 the President's Office transferred custody of most of its historic files to the Archives. At the time of transfer, the collection was referred to as the University of Houston Presidential Papers prior to 1979 and it consisted of forty-two boxes divided into three series. The first series of twenty-one boxes was processed in 1997 as the Presidents' Records 1927-1979. The other two series from this transfer were initially processed in 2001 as the Philip G. Hoffman Papers.
It was decided in 2002 that, while the processing of the University of Houston Presidential Papers Prior to 1979 as two separate collections was acceptable; it was not ideal for research purposes. To improve the accessibility to the collections it was determined that the Philip G. Hoffman Papers and the Presidents' Records should be combined back into one collection, the President's Office Records. As the bulk of the material within President's Records seemed to correspond most directly to the first series (Subject Files) within the Hoffman Papers that is where the majority of re-filing and integration was needed.
The President's Office Records include correspondence, memoranda, publications, clippings, invitations, and related material dating from 1927-1981 that were received or created by the President of the University of Houston. The bulk of the material dates from the mid-1960s to 1978 and was generated during the presidency of Philip G. Hoffman.
The files are rich in materials documenting the history of state support for the University, which was received in 1963, as well as materials showing the rise of student discontent on campus in the late 1960s and early 1970s. See particular student groups such as AABL (Afro-Americans for Black Liberation) for information about the group and its activities and the administration's reaction and response to their demands. This collection also documents the early history of the University of Houston System, with its campuses in Clear Lake, Victoria, and at UH-Downtown. There is also a substantial amount of material relating to the investment scandal of the late 1970s and to the self-study that was undertaken in the mid 1970s.
Photographs in the collection have been transferred to the UH Historical Photographs Collection in the University Archives. A separation sheet notes their original location in the collection and provides a brief description of the items. All student transcripts in the collection have been removed and destroyed, following the Texas Open Records Act. For similar reasons, all materials relating to search committees and personnel decisions have been removed from the collection and are closed to the public.
The collection is arranged into series and sub-series based primarily on how it was originally received in 1985. The nine series are Subject Files, Mission Self-Study, Coordinating Board, President's Cabinet, Investment Investigation, Council of Presidents, Speeches/Oral Interview/Biographical Information, Business/Personal, and President's Christmas Cards. For preservation and access reasons the collection has been re-boxed and re-foldered. New folder titles conform, as closely as possible, to original folder titles, except when the original was obviously incomplete, incorrect, or confusing. Original folder and item order has been maintained whenever possible. Exceptions were made when folders were obviously misfiled or when no order was apparent.
An index to the collection is available. Please contact Special Collections for more information.
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Index Terms
Terms are either Library of Congress Subject Headings or taken from local sources.
Subjects (Persons)
Oberholtzer, E. E. (Edison Ellsworth), b. 1880; Kemmerer, Walter William, 1903-; McElhinney, Charles Flemming; Bruce, Andrew D. (Andrew Davis), d. 1969; Williams, Clanton W. (Clanton Ware), 1904-1975; Hoffman, Phillip G.
Subjects (Organizations)
University of Houston; University of Houston. Office of the President.; University of Houston History; University of Houston Administration
Formats
Correspondence; Memorandums; Invitations; Publications; Clippings
Related Material
Other material related to the President's Office can be found in the following locations:
A.D. Bruce Speeches Collection
A.D. Bruce Scrapbook
Clanton W. Williams Collection
Office of the Business Manager/C.F. McElhinney Papers
Board of Regents Minutes
Acquisition:
Transfer by Dr. Ed Miles, 1985.
Sources
Oberholtzer, Edison Ellsworth. The Growth and Development of the University of Houston: A Summation, March, 1927-May, 1950. Houston, Tex.: University of Houston, 1950.
Nicholson, Patrick. In Time: An Anecdotal History of the First Fifty Years of the University of Houston. Houston, Tex.: Pacesetter Press, c1977.
A Decade of Progress, 1961-1971. Houston: [Office of Information, University of Houston, 1972?]
Harris, Eddie, Bobby Brownstein, Jeannette Burger, and Vince Cohen. The University of Houston Research Project: "The Campaign to Win Full State Support for the University of Houston, 1958-1963": A Research Proposal. [Houston, Tex.: The Authors, 1985]
Detailed Description
- Subject Files (Box 1-50)
  This series is the largest in the collection containing forty-nine boxes of general working files that are presumed to be the President's office files. Materials date from 1927 to 1980, with the bulk of the materials dating between 1960 and 1978. The files cover almost every aspect of the University including student groups, commencement, committees, accreditation, the different colleges, national education related organizations and associations, and the other campuses within the University of Houston System. Files in this series have been arranged alphabetically and then chronologically when necessary.
  - Academic and Professional Women's Assoc., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Academic Dishonesty, 1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic Freedom, Board Policy on, 1964-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Academic Information, Office of, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Academic Vice Presidents Considered, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Accounting, Department of, 1962-1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Accreditation, 1956-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Act Creating the University of Houston, 1923-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Admissions and Records, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Admissions and Records, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Admissions and Records, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Admissions and Records, Dean, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Admissions and Records, Dean, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Admissions and Records, Dean, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Admissions and Records, Dean, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Advisory Board (U of H), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Advisory Board - Communications to Members, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Advisory Board - Executive Committee, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Affirmative Action, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Affirmative Action, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Affirmative Action, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Affirmative Action Speech, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - African Studies Joint Program (Hatch) (TSU), 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Afro-American Studies Program, 1969-1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Agnes Arnold Hall, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - AID - General Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - AID - General Correspondence, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Alcoholic Beverages, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Alcoholic Beverages, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Alpha Lambda Delta, 1965-1976 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Alternatives to Growth, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Alumni Federation, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Alumni Federation, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Alumni Federation, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Alumni Federation, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Alumni Federation, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Alumni Federation, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Federation, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Alumni Federation President's Club, 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - American Academy in Rome, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - American Assembly, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - American Association for Higher Education, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - American Association of University Women, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - American Association of University Women, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - American Association of University Women, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - American College Public Relations Association, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - American Colleges and Universities, 1959-1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - American Council on Education, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - American Council on Education, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - American Council on Education, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - American Council on Education, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - American Council on Education, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - American Council on Education, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - American Council on Education, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - American Council on Education, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - American Council on Education Internship Program, 1968-1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - American Council on Education Internship Program, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - American Council on Education Internship Program, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - American Council on Education Survey, 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - American Geographical Society, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Anderson, Clayton and Co., Inc., 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Anniversary, Silver, 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Anthropology, Department of, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Appropriation Requests, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Archer, Bill, 1972-1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Architecture, College of, 1969-1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Architecture, College of, 1974-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Architecture - Conference in Galveston, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Architecture - National Accrediting Board, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Architecture - National Accrediting Board, 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Architecture - National Accrediting Board, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Architecture - National Accrediting Board, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Architecture - National Accrediting Board, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Architecture - National Accrediting Board, 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Archives, U of H, 1964-1971 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Arnold Foundation, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Art Department, 1951-1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Art, Department of, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Arts and Sciences - By-laws, 1962-1964 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Arts and Sciences, College of, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Arts and Sciences, College of, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Arts and Sciences, College of, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Arts and Sciences, College of, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Arts and Sciences, College of, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Arts and Sciences, College of, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Associated for Higher Education, 1964-1971 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Associated Western Universities, 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Associated Western Universities, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Associated Western Universities, Inc., 1973 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Associated Western Universities, Inc., 1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Associated Western Universities, Inc., 1975 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Associated Western Universities, Inc., 1976 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Association, Memberships of, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Association Memberships, 1965-1973 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Association of American Law Schools, 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Association of Texas Colleges and Universities, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Association of Texas Colleges and Universities, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Association of Texas Colleges and Universities, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Association of Texas Colleges and Universities, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Association of Texas Colleges and Universities, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Association of Upper Level Colleges and Universities, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Association of Urban Universities, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Association of Urban Universities, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Association of Urban Universities, 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Association of Urban Universities, 1969-1978 (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
  - Association of Urban Universities, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Athletics (Box 4-5)
    - Basketball, 1968-1979 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Budgets and Contracts, 1961-1972 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Football, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Football, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Football - Band Night, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Football - Bluebonnet Bowl, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Football - Cotton Bowl, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Football - Cotton Bowl, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Football - Cotton Bowl Association, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Football Games, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Football General, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Football Homecoming Game, 1958-1969 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Football - Houston Oilers, 1968-1974 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Golf, 1964-1973 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Office, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Office, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Office, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Southeastern Conference, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Southeastern Conference, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Southeastern Conference, 1957-1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Southeastern Conference, 1971-1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Southwest Conference, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    - Southwest Conference, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Southwestern Conference, 1952-1957 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Ticket Policies, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Ticket Policies, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Attorney General (Box 5, Folder 9-21)
    - Opinion and Request Procedure, 1951-1965 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Opinion and Request Procedure, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Opinion and Request Procedure, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Opinion and Request Procedure, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Opinion and Request Procedures, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Opinion and Request Procedures, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
    - Opinion and Request Procedures, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 16-17)
    - Opinion and Request Procedures, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Opinion and Request Procedures, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Opinion and Request Procedures, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Opinion and Request Procedures, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Audio-Visual Department, 1961-1968 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Auditorium, Cullen, 1963-1971 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Auditorium, Ezekial Cullen, 1950-1958 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Bailey, Pat University Council, 1972-1976 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Bailey, Pat University Council, 1977-1979 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Baker and Botts, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Baker, Botts, Shepherd and Coates, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Baker, Botts, Shepherd and Coates, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Band - University, 1956-1973 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Bank Accounts, 1971-1976 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Barnes, Ben (Lt. Governor), 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Barthelme, Donald, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Bates College of Law, 1956-1976 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Bates College of Law, 1975-1978 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Bates College of Law, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Bates Hall, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Bates Portrait, Presentation of, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Bender, John R. and Pearl C. (Plaque and Loan Fund), 1964 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Bennet, Rev. Edwin de F., 1969 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Beta Alpha Psi, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Biennial Report, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Biennial Report of the President, 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Blaffer Collection, 1968-1971 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Blaffer Collection, 1972-1974 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Blaffer Collection Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Blaffer Gallery, 1975-1979 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Boat Owned by the University, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Bookstore, 1949-1975 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Booz-Allen & Hamilton, Inc. Management Consultants, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Borden Freshman Prize, 1956-1967 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Briscoe, Dolph - Governor, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Brooks, Chet - Senator, 1969-1974 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Brown and Root, 1963-1972 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Brown Foundation, 1963-1970 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Budget, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Budget, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Budget, 1976-1978 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Budget, 1978-1980 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Budget Appropriations, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Budget - Capital Improvements, 1970-1977 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Budget - Office of the President, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Budget Requisitions, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Budget Requisitions, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Budgets - President's Office, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Building Fund Contributions CLOSED, 1938-1943 (Box 7, Folder 2-5)
  - Building Fund - Miscellaneous, 1937-1938 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Building Fund - Miscellaneous, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Building Fund - Miscellaneous, 1942-1945 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Building Names, 1956-1969 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Building Use Fee, 1968-1974 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Bush, George, 1967-1974 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Business Administration Accreditation, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Business Administration Accreditation, 1958-1964 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Business Administration, College of, 1957-1968 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Business Administration, College of, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Business Administration, College of, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 16-17)
  - Business Administration, College of, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 18)